dr. auntie Galpin here we're back with
five minute fits today I want to talk to
you a little bit about energy systems
and wanted to give you a quick way to
help remember them now what you have to
know to understand these are your
macronutrients
alright so for the most part what we're
talking about here our carbohydrates fat
and protein now protein is actually a
minor player and the role of energy
metabolism we'll talk about what protein
does later so we're really concentrating
on fat and carbohydrate now to make
things actually easier I like to think
about phosphocreatine or or what some
folks called PCR the same thing that you
get when you take creatine as a
supplement it's not truly a
macronutrient but I like to think of it
that way it's gonna help you remember
what they do now if I said we're trying
to create a fire and we're trying to
make some energy and we've got three
possible options
creatine carbohydrate or fat well we've
got some pros and cons each one of these
systems and we'll start off with
creatine imagine creatine is like our
lovely um matches here and I prefer the
lucky Kitty version if you're wondering
so if I take a match here and I hope
this works I don't have to take this
again and now to light it on fire
ah perfect right well the benefit of
using a match to produce energy is it it
lights almost immediately right of
course the drawback is one lasts a few
seconds now in that particular case it
literally lasted like one second but if
I were to turn this stupid wind off
right and I was able to let this candle
burn out until it all they burnt all the
way back down you're still talking maybe
know what 5 10 15 20 seconds something
like that i Ghostface so with
phosphocreatine the benefit is it's a
quick burst of energy but I've only got
so much potential energy I can use and
it only lasts so long eventually I'm
gonna run out of these fire sticks well
next up on our list is carbohydrate
I think of carbohydrate like a newspaper
we have to understand here's actually
fat and carbohydrate are molecularly
very similar in the fact that they're
just big long chains of carbon alright
glucose are
carbohydrate in that fast and actually
is a six carbon chain where fat is
usually eighteen to twenty or thirty
carbons with a bunch stuck together well
my point is if I were to use this
newspaper here and I try not to burn
myself down or burn little Ghostface and
I use this as energy without wind being
around I could light it still pretty
easily not as easy as a match and how
long would it take for me to burn this
newspaper down I don't know what I am
init two minutes something like that
three minutes I don't know something
along the lines of a minute so the
benefit of the newspaper over top of the
phosphocreatine is it lasts quite a bit
longer but we still have a pretty
limited supply right still lights pretty
fast and if we go further down our line
now we've got fat so what's interesting
is remember how I said fat and
carbohydrate are still two just big long
chains of carbon well turns out what's
paper made out of wood right we make
paper out of trees so molecular these
things are very very very similar well
the benefit of fat or wood in this case
is I will have energy for days compared
to my match in my newspaper the fat will
burn considerably longer the downside is
though it takes quite a bit of time for
me to make this a usable energy I would
have to sit here and if you've ever made
a fire before it takes you quite a while
to get wood like this going all right so
that's a quick and easy example of the
benefits and the drawbacks of your
energy systems creatine on this side is
fast but it burns out quickly
carbohydrate in the middle it's pretty
fast but it's gonna also burn out pretty
quickly and then fat comes at the very
end now in another video I'll talk to
you about protein and we'll talk to you
a little bit more about how we oxidize
and metabolize these things and how we
talk about the aerobic and anaerobic
conversions of carbohydrate and the
aerobic conversions
so that's it for now any questions let
me know on social media dr. Andy Galpin
or Antigua calm if not stick around come
back for the 25 and 55 minute versions
of the same talk
you